<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Shunmugavel Mariappan | Engineering Director</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Shunmugavel Mariappan | Engineering Director</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.155.2</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>AI Innovation, ETO &amp; Engineering Excellence</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/ai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-engineering-to-order-eto-model&#34;&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Engineering to Order&amp;rdquo; (ETO) Model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I specialize in bridging the gap between bespoke quality and platform speed. By pioneering the &lt;strong&gt;Engineering to Order&lt;/strong&gt; business model, I’ve turned custom-tailored software products into scalable, high-margin realities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;agentic-ai--workflows&#34;&gt;Agentic AI &amp;amp; Workflows&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beyond RAG:&lt;/strong&gt; Designing autonomous agents that move past simple chat interfaces to execute multi-step business workflows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modern Tech Stack:&lt;/strong&gt; Expert implementation of &lt;strong&gt;LangGraph&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;N8N&lt;/strong&gt;, and Vector DBs to build self-correcting AI systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agentic-Ready APIs:&lt;/strong&gt; Designing API ecosystems that are optimized for consumption by autonomous agents, ensuring future-proof platform scalability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Autonomous Tuning:&lt;/strong&gt; Developed specialized agents for &lt;strong&gt;SQL performance tuning&lt;/strong&gt;, identifying bottlenecks and suggesting index strategies autonomously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cloud-governance--finops-excellence&#34;&gt;Cloud Governance &amp;amp; FinOps Excellence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I lead multi-cloud transformations (AWS, Azure, GCP) that support high-density AI workloads and distributed event-driven architectures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Career Strategic Impact</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/experience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;trimble--engineering-director&#34;&gt;Trimble | Engineering Director&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$20M Portfolio Management &amp;amp; Industry Cloud Pioneering&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Financial Impact:&lt;/strong&gt; Managed a $20M revenue portfolio, serving as the primary engineering partner to Sales and Product leadership to drive a 60% revenue increase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industry Cloud:&lt;/strong&gt; Architected and launched a company-wide Industry Cloud platform from the ground up. This established the architectural standards and automated workflows now used across the transportation and supply chain domains.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Executive Alignment:&lt;/strong&gt; Translated complex customer requirements into a multi-year technical roadmap, improving release efficiency by 25%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Org Design:&lt;/strong&gt; Led the transition to a Single-Threaded Ownership (STO) model, ensuring engineering teams remained agile during a 5x scale-up phase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;verizon--technical-manager&#34;&gt;Verizon | Technical Manager&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Logistics Transformation &amp;amp; Early AI Adoption&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/contact/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;#39;s connect to discuss AI innovation, ETO models, or engineering leadership.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leadership Philosophy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/leadership/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/leadership/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;-strategic-governance--global-influence&#34;&gt;🏛️ Strategic Governance &amp;amp; Global Influence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I lead engineering organizations by bridging technical excellence with high-level business strategy. My leadership extends across regional boundaries to influence global engineering standards and organizational design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;India Engineering Council (IEC) Representative:&lt;/strong&gt; I serve as the segment representative for a collective of &lt;strong&gt;500+ engineering professionals&lt;/strong&gt;, driving strategic alignment between regional talent and global product roadmaps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Global Working Group &amp;amp; Site Leadership:&lt;/strong&gt; As a member of the Site Leadership team, I collaborate with stakeholders in the &lt;strong&gt;US, Canada, Finland, and New Zealand&lt;/strong&gt; to operationalize global initiatives and standardize engineering practices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organizational Scaling &amp;amp; Transformation:&lt;/strong&gt; Successfully managed the transformation of the Chennai engineering hub from a 5-person unit to a multi-functional powerhouse, facilitating a broader &lt;strong&gt;500% organizational scale-up&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cross-Domain Leadership:&lt;/strong&gt; I have successfully applied core leadership frameworks to drive results in both high-scale &lt;strong&gt;Telecom (Verizon - 11 years)&lt;/strong&gt; and complex &lt;strong&gt;Applied AI,Transportation/Logistics &amp;amp; Forestry (Trimble - 7 years)&lt;/strong&gt; environments, proving that excellence is domain-agnostic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Legacy of Transformation:&lt;/strong&gt; During my tenure at &lt;strong&gt;Verizon&lt;/strong&gt;, I managed large-scale engineering transitions that established the foundation for the organization-building expertise I now use to lead the India Engineering Council (IEC).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-building-a-high-performance-culture&#34;&gt;🚀 Building a High-Performance Culture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that engineering output is a direct function of organizational culture. I spearheaded a segment-wide initiative to transition from task-based management to a high-impact, outcome-driven environment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strategic Impact &amp; Milestones</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/impact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/impact/</guid>
      <description>A 19-year legacy of delivering value across Telecom, Applied AI, and Global Logistics.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
