<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Shunmugavel Mariappan | Engineering Director</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Shunmugavel Mariappan | Engineering Director</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.155.2</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>AI Innovation, ETO &amp; Engineering Excellence</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/ai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;ai-as-a-business-multiplier&#34;&gt;AI as a Business Multiplier&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t view AI as a technology choice — I view it as an organizational capability that compounds over time.  Across two decades and two companies, I’ve taken AI from concept to production at scale:  - At &lt;strong&gt;Verizon&lt;/strong&gt;, I deployed ML-driven dispatch automation that moved 20,000+ field technicians from 34% to 80% automated scheduling — a business outcome that saved millions in operational cost. - At &lt;strong&gt;Trimble&lt;/strong&gt;, I championed the adoption of AI/ML across the product portfolio, reducing development cycle time by 40%, cutting test case generation effort by 65%, and building Agentic workflows that transformed how teams work.  The through-line: I build AI strategies that are production-grade, team-adopted, and tied to measurable business value — not R&amp;amp;D experiments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Career Strategic Impact</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/experience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;trimble--engineering-director&#34;&gt;Trimble | Engineering Director&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$20M Portfolio Management &amp;amp; Industry Cloud Pioneering&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Financial Impact:&lt;/strong&gt; Managed a $20M revenue portfolio, serving as the primary engineering partner to Sales and Product leadership to drive a 60% revenue increase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industry Cloud:&lt;/strong&gt; Architected and launched a company-wide Industry Cloud platform from the ground up. This established the architectural standards and automated workflows now used across the transportation and supply chain domains.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Executive Alignment:&lt;/strong&gt; Translated complex customer requirements into a multi-year technical roadmap, improving release efficiency by 25%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Org Design:&lt;/strong&gt; Led the transition to a Single-Threaded Ownership (STO) model, ensuring engineering teams remained agile during a 5x scale-up phase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;verizon--technical-manager&#34;&gt;Verizon | Technical Manager&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Logistics Transformation &amp;amp; Early AI Adoption&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/contact/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;#39;s connect to discuss AI innovation, ETO models, or engineering leadership.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leadership Philosophy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/leadership/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/leadership/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A Note on Scope: My title is Engineering Director, but my operating scope has consistently exceeded that band. As the India Engineering Council (IEC) representative for 500+ engineers at the segment level, the author of org-wide engineering playbooks, I’ve functioned at a Senior Director or VP level for more than a year. The metrics — 500% org growth, 92% retention, $20M portfolio — reflect that scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-strategic-governance--global-influence&#34;&gt;🏛️ Strategic Governance &amp;amp; Global Influence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I lead engineering organizations by bridging technical excellence with high-level business strategy. My leadership extends across regional boundaries to influence global engineering standards and organizational design.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strategic Impact &amp; Milestones</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/impact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/impact/</guid>
      <description>A 19-year legacy of delivering value across Telecom, Applied AI, and Global Logistics.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
